It’s gotten cold.
冷えてきたね
My face stings.
顔が痛いわ
守… 大丈夫かな…
Is Mamoru okay?
Nothing.
何も無い…
どうだった？
無いわ…
Any luck?
I saw nothing.
早季は？
What about you?
どうしよう…
What now?
There has to be something.
ある この雪だもん 必ずあるよ…
There’s snow everywhere.
Mamoru will…
ねえ… 守は…
That’s why we have to look for him!
だから 捜すしかないんだってば
何？
What is it?
Hey…
ねえ
もしかしたら あれじゃない？
Isn’t that what we’re looking for?
これ…
そりの跡…
These are sled tracks.
そり…
A sled…
We were looking for footprints the
whole time, but maybe he took a sled.
足跡ばっかり探してたけど
もしかして そりで…
ずいぶん幅が狭い…
The tracks are quite close to each other.
Mamoru was never great with snow shoes.
守は 長板は
あまり得意じゃなかった
He’s hardly ever used them, in fact.
…というより
ほとんど使えなかったわ
友愛園時代のやつを
引っ張り出してきたのね
Looks like he dug out the sled he used back in Friendship School.
The tracks are deep.
結構 深い
かなり重い荷物を積んでるみたい
He must have brought luggage.
So he stuffed all he could fit into that children’s sled and ran away?
子供用のそりに
積めるだけ積んで家出するなんて
いかにも 守らしい…
It’s something he would do.
お待たせ！
どっち行ったか分かった？
Sorry I took so long.
Do you know which way he went?
分かったわよ
Yes!
八丁標の方に向かったみたいなの
It looks like he went in the direction of the Holy Barrier.
守のお父さんが 置き手紙を
見つけたのは いつなの？
When did Mamoru’s dad find the letter he left behind?
He found it after Mamoru just wouldn’t come down for breakfast, in his room.
いつまでたっても
朝ごはんに来ないから
部屋に行ってみたら あったって
３時間以上 先行してんのか…
So he has three hours or more on us?
荷物をいっぱい乗せてるんなら
He brought a lot of stuff, so he can’t be all that fast.
あんまりスピードは
出ないんじゃない？
うん 途中で
どっちに行こうか迷ったりすれば
I guess.
If he’s been hesitating about where to go,
maybe we can catch up to him in two hours.
２時間くらいで追いつけるかもな
It looks like he’s trying to go somewhere out of the way.
人目につかない所に
行こうとしてるみたいだな
跡を消そうとしてないのも
いかにも 守らしいけど…
It’s also quite like him to not erase his tracks.
なんで 舟を使わなかったのかな？
うん？
Why didn’t he take a boat?
舟の方が全然 早いし
重い荷物も運べるのに
A boat would be much faster and carry a larger load too.
誰かに見られるのが
嫌だったんじゃないかな？
Maybe he didn’t want to be seen by anyone.
他にもあるんじゃない？
Isn’t there another reason?
どんな？
Such as?
It’s definitely easier to escape using the rivers and canals.
水路や川を行ったら
逃げるのは楽よ
But isn’t it also easier to pursue him there?
でも 追いかける方も楽じゃない？
Are you saying he’s—
アイツ もしかして…
八丁標を超えて 山の奥に
行こうとしているのかも…
I think he’s trying to cross the
Holy Barrier and enter the mountains.
Are you kidding me?
ウソだろ…
急がないと 跡が消えちゃう…
We have to hurry or the tracks will fade!
そうだな
Yeah!
だけど まだ
悪鬼が現れないという
However, there was no guarantee that Fiends would never appear again.
保証はないから
行こう
Let’s go.
雪崩だ！
ああ…
An avalanche!
ちょっと これ
はっ…
Hey, look!
どうしたの？
What is it?
Look at this.
これ見て
Probably a queerat.
多分 バケネスミだ…
こんな所で何してるの？
What is it doing here?
分かる訳ないだろ
狩りでもしてるんじゃないの？
How would I know?
Maybe it’s hunting or something?
狩り？
Hunting?
This might be really bad, then.
もし そうだったら
まずいことになるかも
どうして？
Why?
Well, aren’t the footprints following the sled tracks?
ほら そりの跡と ずっと
平行に進んでるんじゃない？
追われてんのかな？
Is it following him?
分かんない…
I’m not sure.
No way…
そんな…
早く早く
守を捜してあげなくちゃ！
Let’s hurry!
We have to find Mamoru!
うん 急ごう
ああ
Yeah! Let’s hurry!
Yeah!
That’s an impressive slope to take on with a children’s sled.
アイツ 子供用のそりで
よく こんな上り方をするよな
What happened to his fear?
怖くないのかな？
He wouldn’t flinch from this hill if
something scarier were chasing him.
もっと怖いものに
追い立てられたら…
こんな坂くらい…
どうしたの？
Is something wrong?
いや 行くぞ
No.
Let’s go.
Yeah.
気をつけろ 凍ってる
分かった
Careful there!
It’s icy!
Got it!
アイツ 途中で
方向転換ができなくなって
I think he couldn’t change course anymore.
行ける所まで行ったんだな
He went as far as he could.
Hey, the tracks stop over there.
ねえ あの先 跡がないよ
どこに行ったか分かる？
Can you tell which way he went?
分からないな
相当な重みがある跡だったのに
No.
Those tracks should have been pretty deep, too.
I’ll take a look at the ridge.
私 上を見てくる
ここから どこに行ったんだ？
Where could he have gone from here?
この辺までは まだ 跡がついてる
There are still tracks until here.
覚！ 見て
Look, Satoru.
もしかしたら ここで守のソリが…
It looks like his sled went off the cliff.
上には 何も無かったわ…
There was nothing up on the ridge.
えっ？
まさか ここで滑って… 下へ？
No… did he slide and fall here?
真理亜
Maria…
とにかく降りてみよう
Let’s go down and take a look.
Even if he really did slide off here, it doesn’t mean he fell all the way to the bottom.
仮に ここから滑り落ちたとしても
いちばん下まで
行ったとは限らないし
うん そうね 行こう 真理亜
Yeah. You’re right.
Let’s go, Maria.
Okay.
分かった
We’re in a snowdrift!
吹きだまりだ
まだ 望みはあるぞ！
There’s still hope!
この雪で
そりが止まったかもしれない
Maybe the snow stopped the sled!
Yeah!
But I don’t see sled tracks anywhere!
でも そりの跡は どこにもないわ
危ないよ 真理亜！ 私にまかせて
Careful, Maria!
Let me do it!
あっ そこ 埋まってる
There! It’s buried there!
掘り出そう 俺がやるから
早季たちは手を出すな
I’ll dig it up!
Don’t interfere, both of you!
どこ？ 守はどこ？
Where? Where is Mamoru?!
もっと下に落ちたの？
Did he fall farther?
落ち着いて 真理亜
Calm down, Maria!
ちょっと待てよ… おかしいよ
Hold on!
This is fishy.
どうして
こんなに完全に埋まってたんだ？
Why was it buried so deep?
雪が降ったからでしょ？
Well, it’s been snowing.
No, it hasn’t.
降ってないよ 守が通った後で
そんなに大量に降ったんなら
If it had snowed that much after Mamoru passed through, the tracks would’ve disappeared as well.
そりの跡は消えて
ここまで追ってこれないよ
We never could’ve followed him here!
Okay, maybe the force of the fall
took the sled deep into the snow?
じゃあ 勢いよく落ちたから
雪の中に潜りこんだんじゃない？
だとしても ここまで
すっぽり隠れないよ
Then it wouldn’t have been covered so neatly.
うん 確かに…
That’s true.
そんなこと
どうだっていいじゃない
Does that even matter?!
守がいないのよ
Mamoru isn’t here!
But it means he might be all right!
だから もしかしたら
守は無事かもしれないんだ
えっ？ どういうこと？
What do you mean?
ここに そりが埋まってた理由は
１つしかない
There’s only one reason the sled would be buried here.
そりが見つからないように
わざと埋めてあったんだ
It was buried so nobody would find it.
Mamoru buried it?
守が埋めたの？
Him, or the queerat that was pursuing him.
それか
守を追っていたバケネズミが…
だけど…
But…
At that time we used the queerats.
その時は バケネズミを使ったの
I’m fairly sure he walked from here on.
おそらく ここからは
歩いて移動したはずだ
We’ll have to look around for places where he could be.
行きそうな所を探りながら
追うしかない
分かった
Got it.
獣道みたいだな
This looks like an animal track.
見て！ あれ
Look! There!
まさか 守を…
Did they kill him?
No, I don’t think so.
いや 多分 違う
Mamoru probably lost consciousness.
守は 気を失ってたんじゃないかな
I think the queerats brought him with them to help him.
バケネズミは 救助するために
連れ帰ったんだと思うよ
どうして そんなことが分かるの？
What makes you think so?
ほら そこ
Look there.
They were avoiding roots and such along the way.
木の根を
わざわざ避けて通っている
もし 死んでるんなら
They wouldn’t have worried about his head hitting the roots if he were dead.
根っこに ぶつかることなんか
気にしないだろ
そうね
うん
That’s true.
Yeah!
また 消えたわ…
They’re gone again.
Don’t worry. This is a good sign.
ううん 大丈夫 これは多分…
ああ 近いんだな
Yeah. They must be close!
どうする？
What now?
正面から行く
Let’s go in through the front.
誰かいるの？
Anyone in?
あっ！ 覚！ 真理亜
Satoru! Maria!
はっ！
ここにいたわ
He’s here!
I’m so relieved.
よかった
みんな 来てくれたの？
You all came to visit?
What do you mean, “visit”?
来てくれたじゃないって
あんまり心配させんなよ
We were worried sick!
ホント無事でよかったけど
あそこで滑って落ちちゃったの？
You look all right, but did you really fall down that cliff?
ああ やっぱり 落ちちゃったんだ
Yeah… I guess I fell.
よく覚えてないんだ
頭を打ったみたいで
I don’t really remember.
I think I hit my head on something and was stumbling through the snow.
もうろうとして
歩けなかったんだけど
スクォンクが僕を見つけて
Squonk found me and brought me here.
ここまで連れてきてくれたんだ
Who?
誰？
スクォンク…
Squonk.
みんな ずっと前に会ってるよ
We met him ages ago.
えっ？
いつ？
When?
あっ！
カゥキッ
もしかして この子…
Wait, was it he who…
Goat 619
Hey, let him down.
ねえ 下ろしてあげて
僕の命の恩人なんだよ
He saved my life.
Yeah, he’s that one.
ああ… 確かに
From the Goat Moth colony.
木蠹蛾の…
カカ… 神様
ありがとうございます
G-Gods…
Th-Thank you…
No, we need to thank you.
ううん こちらこそありがとう
守を助けてくれて
Thank you for saving Mamoru.
No need to thank me.
とんでもございません
神様が お困りになって
おられたのですから
A god was in trouble, so I helped.
キキ… 当然です
It was natural.
助けてもらったのは
ありがたかったよ スクォンク
We appreciate your helping him, Squonk.
でも 何で守の跡をつけたんだ？
But why were you following Mamoru?
はい 私は偶然 そこを通り
I passed the sled tracks by chance.
雪の上の筋を見ました
I wondered which colony had left those tracks and followed to find out.
そして
どこのコロニーのバケネズミが
跡を付けたか考えて
し… 調べに行きました
You were inside the Holy Barrier by chance?
偶然 八丁標の中にいたの？
そんなところで何してたの？
What were you doing there?
What does it matter?
いいじゃない そんなこと
守を助けてくれたのに
Why are you complaining even though he helped Mamoru?
何で そんな文句を
つけるようなことを言うのよ
I’m not complaining, I just…
別に… そういうわけじゃないけど
Here you go, gods.
神様 キキ… どうぞ
ありがとう
Thank you.
とんでもございません
No need to thank me.
残りも… 取ってきます
I’ll come back with the rest.
それより 守 説明してよ
Now explain, Mamoru.
Um… Sorry.
うん… ごめん
A “sorry” is no explanation!
ごめんじゃ 分からないでしょ？
Why did you do this?!
どうして
１人でこんなことしたの！
だって しょうがないじゃないか
Because… I had no choice.
I didn’t want to die!
僕は 死にたくなかったんだ！
死にたくないって どういうこと？
What do you mean, “you didn’t want to die”?
ちゃんと説明して
Explain yourself!
I’m not like you and the others.
僕は みんなとは違うんだよ
呪力も人並み以下だし
My Cantus is fairly weak, and I have no real talents.
他に取り柄があるわけじゃないし
完全に取り残されそうだった
I felt left behind.
That’s not true!
そんなことないよ
遠藤先生も
僕を見る目が冷たいんだ
Mr. Endou has these cold eyes when he looks at me, too.
もう 処分されるリストに
入っていたんだよ
I’ve already been put on the
list of people to be disposed of.
Like X or the girl that used to be in our group.
Ｘとか うちの班にいた女の子や…
Like your sister, Saki.
早季のお姉さんみたいに
I didn’t tell him!
私 言ってない
I know.
知ってるんだよ
みんなでコソコソ話してたの
I know you’ve been keeping secrets from me.
Like the mirror.
鏡のこと
You were trying to keep me in the dark, right?
僕に
聞かせないようにしてたでしょ
You were listening to us?
聞いてたの？
ねえ 守 考えすぎよ
You’re overthinking this, Mamoru.
ネコダマシが来たんだよ
A copycat came.
What?
どういうことなの？
２回 見たんだ
I saw it twice.
The first time was four days ago.
最初は４日前
暗くなってから
家に帰ってきたとき
When I was coming home after dark, I felt like something was tailing me.
何か後ろをつけてきてる感じが
したんだ
ネコダマシの姿は見えなかった
I didn’t see the copycat itself,
でも何か隠れているのは
分かったんだ
but I knew something was hiding there.
ものすごく大きな影だった
It was a really big shadow.
でも
気のせいだったんじゃないの？
Are you sure it wasn’t just your imagination?
木か何かの影が
かがり火で大きく見えたとか
A tree or something would cast
a big shadow from a firelight.
Yeah!
そうそう もし本当に
ネコダマシが来たんだったら
If it really were a copycat, it should’ve attacked you.
もっと早く襲いかかるはずよ
I’m not so sure.
それは どうかな？
There’s a lot of tales about copycats, but
there’s one aspect they all disturbingly share.
ネコダマシの話は
いろいろ あるけど
気持ち悪いぐらい
共通してるとこがあるんだ
獲物を襲う前に１回
They apparently practice tailing you first before attacking you.
予行演習みたく 跡をつけるって
Yeah.
うん 僕もその時は 多分
I don’t think it was going to attack me then.
襲う気は なかったんだと思う
だけど 昨日はそうじゃなかった
But yesterday was different.
Yesterday? Oh, no…
昨日？ まさか…
昨日の放課後だよ
It was yesterday after school.
I stayed behind alone for my supplementary classes.
補習で１人だけ居残りだったんだ
When I was about to pack up and go home, Mr. Endou told me to put some leftover printouts away in the storage room.
終わって帰ろうとしたとき
遠藤先生が備品保管庫に
余ったプリントを
しまっておいてくれって
あの中庭に行く途中にある部屋？
The one in the hallway leading to the inner yard?
Yes.
大した枚数じゃないし
There weren’t many pages.
何で僕に頼むのかなって思ってた
I was wondering why he’d ask me to do that.
No…
ダメだ
ダメだ ダメだ…
No…
No… No…
No!
I’m absolutely certain.
間違いないよ
It was a copycat.
あれはネコダマシだったんだ
Yesterday, I…
昨日 私…
補習が終わるまで
待ってるつもりだったの
I was going to wait for you until
supplementary classes had ended.
But they told me to go home because it would take too long.
でも長くかかるから
帰りなさいって言われたの
最初から守を１人にして
殺すつもりだったのね
They wanted to isolate you and
then kill you from the beginning.
Hang on there.
でも ちょっと待てよ
Why do they want to get rid of Mamoru?
何で
守を処分しなきゃなんないんだ
His Cantus is pretty average, and there’s nothing wrong with his personality!
呪力も 別に人並みだし
性格だって全然 問題ないだろ？
He’s quiet and cooperative!
いつも穏やかで協調性も高いのに
How would I know?
そんなこと知らないわよ！
He saw a copycat!
守はネコダマシを見ているのよ？
それも２回も！
Twice at that!
これ以上 何を疑うことがあるのよ
How can you still doubt him?
早季 早季も何とか言ってよ！
Saki!
Say something, Saki!
ネコダマシを見たとき
思い出したんだ
I remembered when I saw the copycat.
僕はアイツを
前に見たことがあるんだよ
I had…
…seen that cat before.
Seriously? Mamoru?
ホントか？ 守…
どうしても
はっきりとは思い出せないんだ
I just can’t remember clearly, even if I try.
I think it’s part of a larger memory that they erased.
多分 消された記憶の
一部なんだと思うが
でも 僕は…
But I remember going into the inner yard and hiding behind one of the little huts.
確かに中庭に入って
小屋の影に隠れてた
そしたら 扉が開いて
中からアイツが…
Then one of the doors opened and that copycat came out!
ネコダマシが出てきたんだ
それ 私も覚えてる
I remember that too.
I was there too!
私も… そこにいた
守を見つけて 連れ戻せばいい
という 甘いもくろみは
Our naive plan of finding Mamoru and bringing him back to the village was falling apart.
粉々に打ち砕かれてしまった
What were our options at that point?
私たちは
これからどうすればいいのだろう
Episode Thirteen
Reunion
Nakisou na aoringo kakaeteru mune no oku
泣きそうな青リンゴ  抱えてる胸の奥
In my chest, I carry a green apple that wets my eyes
Korogatte tsuyogatte
転がって  強がって
I fall over yet pretend to be strong
Kyuukutsu na sora niramu
窮屈な空睨む
I glower at the sky and it seems to suffocate me
Unmei ni juujun ni
運命に従順に
Do I look like I'd wait quietly
Jukusu no wo matsu mon ka
熟すのを待つもんか
For destiny to ripen it?
Sen no kaze
千の風
The winds
Agaite sakende
あがいて  叫んで
I struggle and scream
Fuke fuke
吹け吹け
Blow and blow
Watashi wa shabondama
わたしはしゃぼん玉
I'm a soap bubble
Soredemo shinjiteru
それでも信じてる
And still I have faith
Yokisenu arashi ni
予期せぬ  嵐に
In a sudden storm
Joushou shite kakou shite
上昇して  下降して
I rise and fall
Aragau shabondama
あらがうしゃぼん玉
I fight, soap bubble that I am
Soredemo ikiteku
それでも生きてく
And still I live on
Hajikeru shunkan niji hanate
弾ける瞬間  虹、放て
I make a rainbow when I burst
Why is it always us?
どうして私たちだけが…
I don’t want to die!
僕… 死にたくない！
We’ll always be together from now on.
これからは ずっと一緒よ
All right?
いいわね 約束よ
Promise me.
もう会えないの？
Will I ever see you again?
Of course you will.
そんなことないわ
きっとまた会えるから
I’m sure we’ll meet again.